# SAGHAR HOSSEINI

Seattle, Washington · 949-419-4538
Saghar.hossaini@gmail.com · <u>linkedin.com/in/sagharh</u>

I am a Senior Scientist at Microsoft Research where I am primarily focused on building the next generation of intelligence and language understanding for improving enterprise productivity. I utilize the latest techniques in Machine Learning (ML) including Deep Learning approaches and Natural Language Understanding (NLU). I received my PhD in 2016 from University of Washington and have co-authored several papers in the field of NLU and distributed ML.

## **EXPERIENCE**

## **AUGUST 2016 - PRESENT**

## **SENIOR SCIENTIST, MICROSOFT RESEARCH, REDMOND, WA**

As an applied scientist in our team, I work in a small team of scientists and engineers, collaborating closely with other research and product teams across Microsoft. I work with cutting-edge technology on highly visible and impactful projects that aim to bring intelligence with clear user value to existing and new Microsoft products. I participate in research to advance the state of the art in machine learning and language understanding technologies. I think creatively, and proactively and in a self-driven manner to solve existing problems and identify new opportunities. I deploy machine learning models in production environments and publishing in top tier conferences (e.g., ACL, WWW, NIPS, ICML, SIGIR, etc.)

## **JUNE 2014 – SEPTEMBER 2014**

## **RESEARCH INTERN, MICROSOFT RESEARCH, REDMOND, WA**

I worked with Misha Bilenko, Kenneth Tran, and Lin Xiao on implementing a fast and reliable algorithm for learning on large scale data sets, called Stochastic Dual Coordinate Ascent (SDCA), to be included in the **Microsoft Azure**.

### **JUNE 2016 - JULY 2016**

## RESEARCH SCIENTIST III, UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON, SEATTLE, WA

I developed online algorithms for community detection and topology estimation in large timevarying social networks based on mixed membership model and opinion dynamics.

#### SEPTEMBER 2011 - MARCH 2016

## **GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT, UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON, SEATTLE, WA**

I developed online distributed optimization algorithms and worked on distributed machine learning algorithms and their applications in large scale networks under the guidance of Professor Mehran Mesbahi.

# **EDUCATION**

#### **MARCH 2016**

**PHD,** AERONAUTICS & ASTRONAUTICS, UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON, SEATTLE, WA

I was advised by Professor Mehran Mesbahi and had a 3.97 GPA.

I received the Amelia Earhart fellowship award from Zonta International Foundation twice. This fellowship is awarded to 35 fellows around the globe each year who are pursuing advanced studies in the aerospace-related sciences. I received the Graduate School Top Scholars Award from University of Washington and the best session presentation award from American Control conference.

#### **SEPTEMBER 2011**

**MASTER OF SCIENCE,** AEROSPACE ENGINEERING, UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, IRVINE, CA

I was advised by Professor Benjamin Vilac and had a 3.97 GPA. I received three graduate fellowship awards from University of California and one award from the Society of Women Engineers.

#### **SEPTEMBER 2008**

**BACHELOR OF SCIENCE,** AEROSPACE ENGINEERING, SHARIF UNIVERSITY OF TECHNOLOGY, TEHRAN, IRAN

I was a member of Sharif University's swimming team and participating in competitions.

# **SKILLS**

- Professional Activities: Reviewer for ACL, SIGIR and WWW
- Programming languages: Python, C#, SQL
- Core Technologies: PyTorch, TensorFlow, scikit-learn

## SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

For a full list of publications see <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=XhTT61UAAAAJ&hl=en">https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=XhTT61UAAAAJ&hl=en</a>

- Jieyu Zhao, Subhabrata (Subho) Mukherjee, Saghar Hosseini, Kai-Wei Chang, Ahmed Hassan Awadallah, "Gender Bias in Multilingual Embeddings and Cross-Lingual Transfer", Annual Conference of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL 2020), July 2020
- Ahmed Elgohary, Saghar Hosseini, Ahmed Hassan Awadallah, "Speak to your parser: Interactive Text-to-SQL with natural language feedback", Annual Conference of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL 2020), July 2020
- Petar Stojanov, Ahmed Hassan Awadallah, Paul Bennett, Saghar Hosseini, "On Domain Transfer When Predicting Intent in Text", NeurIPS Workshop on Document Intelligence, December 2019
- Wei Wang, Saghar Hosseini, Ahmed Hassan Awadallah, Paul Bennett, Chris Quirk, "Context-Aware Intent Identification in Email Conversations", Proceedings of the 42nd Annual International ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR 2019), July 2019
- Saghar Hosseini, Airlie Chapman, and M. Mesbahi, "Online Distributed Optimization on Dynamic Networks," The IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control, 2016